hey this is jerry from blizzstudio and
in this unity tutorial we're going to
look at the train tools that are built
into unity and then also the terrain
tool asset that you can download as a
package so if you're ready to start
building 3d terrains let's go okay so
here i am in unity and this tutorial is
a little bit of a long one so i hope
that you stick with me now what are we
gonna cover we are covering creating
terrain all right so to get started i've
already imported a character that i
downloaded from mixamo into my game the
next thing i need to do is to go ahead
and go over to
assetstore.unity.com and i've downloaded
three different asset packs the first
one is the low poly environment nature
pack and the one thing that you need to
know with a lot of the asset packs i am
starting a urp project and you just need
to make sure that the asset packs that
you download will work with urp a lot of
them will have a
component that you install after you
download this that will then upgrade the
materials to urp so i'm using the low
poly environment nature pack which is
free i'm also using the fantasy skybox
which is free as well
and then we are going to
in unity download unity's new terrain
tools asset pack from the package
manager and then with that it has a set
of downloads that you can extend the
built-in terrain tools set
with this sample pack as well so this is
terrain sample pack asset and we'll go
over to unity so in unity let's take a
look at the package manager the option
that you need to download is terrain
tools now there is already built-in
terrain tools in unity this just extends
and adds a lot more features to it so go
ahead and download that and then here is
the link for the download asset pack
which is this terrain sample asset pack
it'll be good for you to have for this
particular tutorial
all right now with that being said let's
go ahead and close this i've already
installed all of that so let's jump
right into the terrain so for me to go
ahead and start a terrain i am going to
go ahead to 3d object
and hit terrain this creates a terrain
that's fairly large now my character
looks big is because the character is
way up in the sky
and my terrain is way down low so for us
to go ahead and set this up we want to
make sure we have our terrain selected
and then in the terrain component window
you can see that we've got a bunch of
different buttons across the top see
with our paint train tab selected we can
go and go to set height
and then down at the bottom we're going
to change this to be 100 and then we're
going to flatten tile so what that's
going to do is bring the level of our
terrain up so we can then both decrease
and increase the height
boom all of a sudden our terrain is way
higher now we need to go ahead and
instead of set height we're going to go
back to raise and lower terrain this is
where we can start to increase and
decrease the terrain to make it look
like mountains and hills and valleys
so i'm going to go ahead and just zoom
out
so you can see the size of my character
in relation to
the terrain
we have all these brushes to then be
able to use to paint hills and valleys
onto our terrain there's a couple keys
that you want to use
they're the a d s and control key if you
hold the 8 key you can decrease and
increase the strength of the brush
if you hold the s key that changes the
size so i'm just hitting the key and
then moving my cursor left and right
and then the d key allows you to rotate
your train brush
and then the control key
inverses it so that it's decreasing the
size of the train versus increasing the
size of the train so i'm going to go
ahead and just paint out a little bit of
terrain real quick
we now have some features in our terrain
so i'm going to go ahead and go back to
my player
and now it's below the train so what i
need to do is to just go ahead and move
the character up
there we go and i've also went ahead and
i've attached the main camera to the
player and so that that that way it
gives us a place to see or how we can
see the player within the environment
i'm gonna go ahead and just rotate my
player real quick
all right so now we have this terrain
with some features we need to actually
go ahead and start coloring it the way
we're going to do that is to paint
texture so with the terrain selected i'm
going to go back to my paint terrain tab
i'm going to select paint texture and
then down at the bottom we can go ahead
and start adding layers to actually
paint onto our terrain
so i'm going to first add the layer i
have some of the predefined textures
that we can add i'm going to go ahead
and just use this grass a texture
and then boom now our terrain has some
texture to it now i think the grass is
just a little bit small so what i'm
going to do is to just select the name
right next to the tile i'm going to
select that and then i can change the
size of the grass within this
environment so i'm going to go ahead and
just increase this to maybe 20 by 20 and
i think that looks a little bit better
now the next thing i want to do is to go
ahead and paint a path onto my terrain
as well
so for me to be able to do that i'm
going to go back to my terrain and i
need to add another layer so i'm going
to go ahead and add layer
and i'm going to find something that
looks like it would be path and so i'm
going to go ahead and just use this sand
terrain
and then what i can do is i can go and
select maybe this smooth brush
and let's go back to our scene view
and i need to make it way smaller i want
to zoom in to where my players at and
then we can go ahead and start painting
so with my sand selected i'm going to go
ahead and just start painting
right a path onto my terrain now i'm
going to go ahead and just increase the
strength here just a little bit and you
can start to see how there's just a
little bit of a linear aspect what this
path looks like and we want to make sure
that this has a little bit higher
resolution so we have a nice smooth
transition so to do that what we're
going to do is go to window terrain
terrain toolbox and then right here
we've got the option of choosing a
texture resolution and we're going to
set the control texture resolution here
a little bit higher so i'm going to go
to 2048 apply to select a train now we
can just close that window
and then our path will be a lot smoother
so let me go ahead and just paint out a
path real quick and we'll be right back
so i have a little bit of a path painted
out i'm going to go ahead and just
continue by adding a new layer and what
i want to do is just i don't want the
path to be right on the grass and so
what i'm going to do is just add a
little bit of a transition in between
the path and the grass so i've got a
couple different options of elements
here i'm going to go ahead and just
choose this grass soil terrain and let's
go ahead and choose that one and then i
can go ahead and paint this as well
cool so there we go we now have a little
bit of a path that our character can
travel along and of course those
mountains that are in the distance
aren't gonna be covered in grass they're
gonna be covered in rocks so let's go
ahead and add a new layer and let's just
find a nice rock terrain okay so i'm
gonna go ahead and paint some of the
mountains in the distance to have rock
drain
okay now that we have some rocky terrain
let's go ahead and add a little bit of
snow
so let's add a new layer
and i've got a snow terrain option
and then i'm going to go ahead and just
take the brush size way down
so we can be very selective about where
we're painting this
okay so the next thing that i want to do
is currently my path is
just flat along the terrain and i want
that path because it is a path where
people have traveled i want it to be
slightly indented so what we're going to
do is go back to our terrain
and we're going to go ahead and raise
and lower i want to go ahead and indent
that path so i'm going to take that
strength way down as well so i want the
path to be slightly indented so for me
to do that i just need to hold down the
control key
and i can paint
a dent into the path
the next thing i want to do is to go
ahead and paint on some grass so for me
to do that i need to go to my
grass tab
and we can go ahead and edit details
and i'm going to add some grass texture
we can add meshes or we can add the
texture i'm gonna go ahead and add a
texture so let's go ahead and add detail
and i'm gonna just
choose my brush grass right here
and then i have some options for how big
this is in both a min and a max and then
a height min and max and you can always
go back and edit these as well so i'm
going to go ahead and just
go 0.2 and maybe point
eight
i'll do the same thing on the height
so it'll give us just a little bit of a
variety
and i'm gonna go ahead and add that
grass
and then i can now just start painting
grass onto the terrain so i've got the
option of choosing the brush size the
opacity which is how thick the grass is
going to be as well as the target
strength
so boom you can see how easy it is just
to start painting grass all over your
terrain
and if you do accidentally paint some
grass onto your path you can easily go
ahead and delete that as well so i'm
going to just zoom into my path here
take my brush size down and then i can
just hold the ctrl key
and boom now i'm just removing
the grass
now this grass doesn't really look all
that great right now so what i want to
do is i'm going to go ahead and go to my
edit details and i'm going to edit this
grass so what we can do is we can start
playing around with the color as the
grass is on the ground
so we can change what the healthy color
looks like so i'm going to just change
this to be a little bit more
in terms with the regular grass
and there we go i can also add more
details so i'm going to go ahead and
just edit details and add more grass
texture
so let's find a different type of grass
and let's maybe go ahead and add some
flowers this time so i'm going to go
ahead and add flowers
now the next thing we need is some trees
in our train okay so what i'm going to
do is go to my paint trees tab
and then with that we can go ahead and
edit trees i'm going to add a tree
so we're going to select a tree to use
and even though these look pink they
actually do paint out as regular
graphics so i'm going to choose a pine
tree go ahead and select ok and then i'm
going to add that
and then with this again i can choose
the brush size
and then how we're going to paint that
tree and i can choose some randomization
of the tree height so let's just start
placing a few trees
boom so that's pretty pretty dense
there's a lot of different settings that
you can use here but i'm going to go
ahead and just undo that real quick and
as opposed to painting all these trees
in we can go ahead and use this this
mass place trees option so i'm going to
go ahead and select that
and then with that we're going to place
10 000 trees across our whole terrain
so i'm gonna go ahead and just hit place
and then boom all of a sudden now we
have trees across our whole train then
you can go back and start filling in or
removing as you see fit so i'm gonna go
ahead and just remove remove a few here
so again hold down the control key and
we can just deselect or de-paint some of
those trees and then we can also just go
back and add more trees as needed
boom there we go so that's actually
looking pretty good now the next thing i
need to do is to go ahead and maybe
paint in some some brush as well so i'm
gonna some bushes so i'm gonna edit
trees add a new tree and then we also
have some options here for different
types of bushes so i'm gonna go ahead
and just add one of those and in this
case i'm just gonna go ahead and paint
down a few of these
cool this is looking pretty good but we
can make it look just a little bit
better so the first thing i want to do
is to go over to my lighting tab and if
you don't have that you can go to window
rendering lighting
and we want to go ahead and use our free
sky box that we downloaded so for us to
do that let's go ahead and in the
environment part of our lighting tab we
can go ahead and click on skybox
material
and i now have all of the materials that
are in my game i'm going to go ahead and
just try out a couple of these different
sky boxes to see what really looks good
yeah that one looks actually pretty good
so i'm going to go ahead and use that
then the next thing we need to do is we
can turn on fog still in my environment
tab i'm going to go ahead and turn on
fog
and then we can choose what the fog
color is by default this fog color is
gray
but we can change it to whatever color
we want and because i have a little bit
of red in the sky i'm going to go ahead
and just choose to have this as a little
bit red
and then we can change the density so
how thick that fog is and how far away
it is so let's just maybe take that down
to two so we can see down just a little
bit further in the distance
so the next thing that we can do is to
also add some post processing because
this started out as a urp project post
processing is installed so what i can do
is to easily go to volume
create a new global volume and i'm going
to just call this post
processing
and then with that i'm going to go ahead
and in my inspector i'm going to add a
new post-processing volume and now i
have that post-processing volume
installed now i can just select the
post-processing
and then start adding overrides so in
this case we can add post-processing
override we can add maybe just a touch
of bloom
and increase the intensity slightly
and for us to be able to see that we
need to make sure that our main camera
also has rendering and post processing
checked by default that is off so let's
go back to our post-processing volume
boom there we go so let's go ahead and
hit play to see how this actually looks
yeah i'm digging it so there you go
there is the terrain tool and a little
bit of the post-processing and the fog
for our terrain hey i hope you enjoyed
that tutorial and it's something you can
use for your game don't forget to hit
like subscribe and that little bell icon
down there so you know when the next
tutorial is available until next time